曾经，不久前的非洲深部
Once, not long ago,
in deepest Africa,
一片繁茂、野性、神奇的热带雨林
a great rain forest,
一直鲜为人知
a wild, magical land,
barely touched by humankind.
这是幽深丛林中特别的一天
It's a special day in the dark
heart of this forest.
一个新生命诞生
There's a new life,
一个叫做奥斯卡的小男宝宝
a precious baby boy named Oscar.
是什么令他如此特殊呢？
What's so special
about this little guy?
一些惊人之举即将改变他的一生
Well, something truly amazing
will transform his life.
这就是我们即将讲述的故事
And that's what our
story is all about.
黑猩猩
在这片热带雨林下面
Beneath this rain forest canopy
是一个你我从未见过的世界
is a world that you or I
may never set eyes on.
一个没有人烟的地方
It's a world with few people,
但是依旧充满了戏剧、悲伤，和欢乐
but still, it's full of drama,
sadness, and joy.
《That Man》 by Caro Emerald
自从小奥斯卡陪伴他妈妈以来
About three months have passed
三个月已经过去了
since little Oscar brought
light into his mother's life.
没有什么让伊沙更开心了
Isha couldn't be happier
with her new baby boy.
奥斯卡的世界里始终离不开妈妈
Oscar's world revolves around Mom,
但是群里还有35只黑猩猩
but there are 35 other chimpanzees
in his group
他们一起组成了一个大家庭
that make a kind of extended family,
一个不离不弃的大家庭
and they're never far away.
或许等到小奥斯卡50岁的时候
Perhaps one day Oscar will become
也会和他的老爷爷一样
an old-timer like Grandpa,
华发苍颜
who will turn 50 this year.
但是这里也有其他的小孩
But there are other kids, too.
他们将会是小奥斯卡的好伙伴
They'll become Oscar's playmates.
只有在丛林深处
It's a rich society,
才会如此的富饶
but in the heart of the jungle.
距离小奥斯卡成年还有20多年
Now, Oscar won't be
in his prime until he's over 20,
但总有一天他会长得和这个家伙一样
but one day, he'll look like this big guy.
他叫弗雷迪，一位高大威猛的首领
This is Freddy,
and he's large and in charge.
他的白胡子显露出
His white beard shows his years
丰富的智慧和经验
of wisdom and experience.
现在，弗雷迪地位很稳
Right now, Freddy is untouchable.
和其他动物的首领一样
And like most alpha males,
他不能对群里的后来者掉以轻心
he couldn't care less
about the young upstarts
这些晚辈成天想着接过弗雷迪的地位
who would just love
to take over his job someday.
喂 喂，别想得太远
Yeah, yeah. Seen it all before.
在这之前你还是动动脑子如何生存
You need brains
to make a living in this forest.
丛林里的工具箱能帮上大忙
The jungle toolbox can help,
但你需要知道如何去使用
but only if you're bright
enough to use it.
有时需要家庭教育
Sometimes it just takes
a little home-schooling
身边朋友家人的指导
available from your friends and family.
看到了吗？就像这样
See? Like this.
到手
Right there.
连鲁弗斯最后也学会了
Even Rufus catches on, eventually.
就这样. 虫子被黏在棍棒上.
There you go. Bugs on a stick.
奥斯卡独立的日子来临了
It's finally time for Oscar
to leave his mother's side.
对于伊沙的小儿子来说，今天是独立日
For Isha 's little boy,
this is independence day,
独立的一小步
and independence
comes one step at a time.
一天独立一点点就足够了
Well, that's enough
independence for one day.
一群成年黑星星掌管着奥斯卡的家，
Oscar's forest home is a prime
piece of chimpanzee real estate
一片郁郁葱葱却又生存艰难的丛林
that appears rich and lush,
but it's a hard place to make a living.
丛林本身也是一个富有生机的生命
The jungle itself is a living,
breathing thing
他可不想被活活吃掉
that doesn't want to be eaten.
寻找食物是主要的工作
Finding food here is a full-time job
整个家庭成员都要参与
that involves the whole family,
包括奥斯卡
including Oscar.
现在他成熟了一点点
Now that he's grown up a little,
他能够自己探路了
he can start to explore on his own.
但是有便车搭 他也不会拒绝
But he's not above
catching a lift when he can.
真是的，有便车搭为什么还要自己走呢？
Really, why walk
when you can hitch a ride?
妈妈，快走
Keep it moving, Mom.
弗雷迪带领着大家寻找午餐
Freddy leads the search for breakfast.
他们行动的时候需要有人指引
It helps to have someone who
knows where they're going,
尤其是要找的大餐总不在同一个“餐馆”
especially when the restaurant
is never in the same place.
今天的大餐甚至不在隔壁
Today the diner isn't even
in the same neighborhood.
为了寻找水果大餐
To find the fruit they'll need,
他们需要穿梭很远
they will have to travel much further
中途还需要休息
and take a risk.
弗雷迪知道现在唯一可摘的水果
Freddy knows the only fruit
available now
远在他们的领域边缘
is on the far side of their kingdom,
这是一个危险的地带
out of their safe zone.
在这块边界上，他们已经战略好几代了
This border has been
a battleground for generations.
每个人都高度戒备
Everyone is on maximum alert
小心翼翼地前行
and treads as quietly as possible.
弗雷迪带领着大家靠近敌人
Freddy is leading them close
to their greatest enemies.
这条绵延的山脊
This ridge marks the start of territory
是对手的领地标志
owned by a group
of rival chimpanzees.
禁果近在咫尺
The forbidden fruit is finally in reach.
嘘 奥斯卡 嘘
Shh, Oscar. Shh.
弗雷迪发现对方要多出一两个人
Freddy sees his team
are outnumbered two to one.
他们有一个强大的首领
The enemy has a formidable leader,
伤疤
Scar.
伤疤和他的手下
He and his team have had Freddy
盯上弗雷迪已经多年了
in their sights for years.
奥斯卡紧紧靠着伊沙，他们不敢妄动一步
Oscar clings to Isha.
They dare not make a move.
对手已经嗅到了他们气息
The rivals have caught their scent.
奥斯卡他们已命悬一线
Oscar and the others
are in real danger.
伤疤用猛击发号进攻命令，对于伊沙来说，不跑只有死路一条
Scar's drum is a threat.
For Isha, it's run or die.
弗雷迪带着大家逃跑
Freddy leads the escape.
在追赶中冲散弗雷迪的队伍之后
By running off Freddy's group,
伤疤他们宣告小胜一筹
their enemies have claimed
a small victory.
但这还只是个开始
But that's just the beginning.
伤疤他们意在拿下整场战争
Scar and his troops are intent
on winning the war,
而不仅仅是一场小胜
not just a single battle.
战利品
The prize,
是弗雷迪家里的一片坚果园
a grove of nut trees
in the center of Freddy's land.
这块果园是艰险丛林里难得的宝地
The grove is an oasis of food
in this difficult forest
如果伤疤他们想要生长壮大
and one that Scar's army
has to conquer
就必须拿下这块宝地
if they're going to survive and thrive.
伊沙深知伤疤是小奥斯卡最大的威胁
Isha knows that Scar
is the greatest threat to little Oscar,
稍不注意就会引起口角之争
and the run-in
was too close for comfort.
她将尽自己最大的努力保护奥斯卡
She'll do everything possible
to keep her son safe.
奥斯卡仍需要靠母乳成长
Oscar will rely on his mother's
milk for a good while yet,
而伊沙的母乳
and to keep that milk flowing
依赖着弗雷迪领域里的这片坚果园
Isha relies on the rich nuts
in Freddy's kingdom.
这片深受伤疤垂涎的果园
The magnificent nut groves,
so sought-after by Scar,
依靠着这里的肥沃土地
thrive here because of the rich soil,
和另一种神奇营养成分
and another magic ingredient,
生命之泉
life-giving water.
在瀑布之下，弗雷迪的领地正中心
Beneath the waterfall,
in the heart of Freddy's territory,
坚果正在成熟
the nuts are coming into season
现在正是收获的季节
and it's time for a feast.
这些坚果美味可口，营养丰富，令人爱不释手
They're delicious, nutritious,
and you can't eat just one.
一次带很多似乎不现实
It seems impossible to have too many.
但是没有袋子你怎么装呢？
But how do you carry them
without a bag?
你得动下脑子了
You've got to be creative.
嗯... 把他们捧在手心
Hmm. Put them over in this hand.
有人见过这个吗？
Anybody watching this?
成熟的坚果可以被嗅出来
The ripest nuts can be sniffed out.
但是有些却是很难被敲碎
But these are also
the hardest to break into.
他们需要合适的工具和正确的方法
They require the right tool
for the right job.
表面上看着很容易
It looks easier than it is,
实际上需要这些伙计们花费数年才能掌握
and the technique takes these
guys many years to master.
对 就是这样
Yeah, here we go. Yum, yum.
有时候打开坚果的最佳办法并不是用工具
Sometimes the best tool
for getting nuts isn't a tool at all.
没错，有一位好母亲就行了
Yup, it's good old Mom.
真是笔不错的“交易”
It's a pretty sweet deal.
但是妈妈只能照顾几年的时间
But Mom will only help out
for a couple of years.
最后他们还是需要自己动手
Then they'll have to take
a shot at it themselves.
真的有这么难吗？
Really, how hard can it be?
奥斯卡正在上坚果课
Oscar is in nut preschool.
可是他的锤子有点不对劲
There's something wrong
with this hammer.
这砸不开坚果的！
It won't hit the nut!
毫无疑问是锤子不行
Yup, definitely the hammer.
哈哈 来个更大的！
Of course. A bigger one!
这是块烂木头!
This is defective!
他们从来不用已经用过的木头
They just don't make logs
like they used to.
我知道了.肯定是坚果的问题
All right. It has to be the nut.
哈哈  等等  他们是在用石头吗？
Whoa, whoa, hold on.
They're using rocks?
可是没人告诉他们啊
No one said anything about rocks.
噢，我知道了，他们知道石头更硬
Oh, I get it.
They must be harder than wood.
当坚果遇上石头...
Mr. Nut, meet Mr. Rock.
便诞生了“啪啪”
Come to Papa.
好极了！敲开一个
Yes! Okay, that's one.
奥斯卡的坚果吃光了
Now Oscar's out of nuts.
他需要丢下锤子去进货
He'll have to leave
his hammer to stock up.
菜鸟错误
Rookie mistake.
我盯你小子一天了
I had an eye on that kid all day.
傻小子
What an idiot.
坚果大餐过后，
After all those nuts,
没人在丛林里摇晃
nobody's swinging through the trees.
没错，现在是好好休息消化的时间
Yes, it's time to rest and digest.
连我们的小奥斯卡都呼呼大睡
Even our boy Oscar's knocked out.
饱餐之后需要休息好几个小时
It can take hours
to sleep off a big meal,
但是丛林仍旧生机勃勃
but the jungle never rests.
正午当头的时候
In the heat of day,
父母们只想享受一下宁静的生活
the parents just want a few
minutes of peace and quiet,
但是孩子们可不这么想
but the kids have other ideas.
特别是奥斯卡
Especially Oscar.
来吧，伙伴们！
Come on up, guys!
这里有数不清的树
A million trees in this forest
你要怎么玩过我
and you have to play over me.
我还在睡觉 我还在睡觉!
I'm sleeping. I am still sleeping!
看看多么宓囊辽
Poor Isha. Just look at her.
可怜她一手紧紧的抓着奥斯卡
She really does have
her hands full with Oscar,
但是她的耐心却是相当足
but her patience
never seems to run out.
奥斯卡是只幸运的黑猩猩
Oscar's one lucky young chimp.
伤疤和他的那群暴徒日益临近
Scar and his thugs
are a growing threat.
食物在他的领地里依旧稀贵
Food is still scarce in their territory.
如果一切照旧
If nothing changes,
他们将被迫离开果园
they'll be forced to make
a move on the nut groves.
如果成功
If they succeed,
弗雷迪他们将被驱逐
Freddy and his group will be exiled
永远从这里消失
from their homeland forever.
渐老的伤疤一直受到群内的压力
The aging Scar is under
constant pressure from within.
他群里的雄性黑猩猩都很强
The males in his team are so powerful
随便哪一个都可能取代他
that any one of them could
challenge him as leader,
他也深知这点
and he knows it.
等级制度维系着种群的和睦
Grooming helps hold
this volatile team together
也提醒着每位成员谁才是老大
and reminds everyone who's boss.
没有这点，他们将是一盘散沙
Without it, there would be anarchy.
等级制度短期还不会变
This hierarchy may hold
in the short term,
但是伤疤还能撑多久呢？
but how long can Scar
count on his men?
远在西边
Far to the west,
瀑布下面一种奇异的果子已经成熟
a special fruit has come into
season beneath the waterfall.
沙克格劳荻斯（音译）
Sacoglottis.
连说三遍看看
Trying saying that three times fast.
弗雷迪知道果子的价值
Freddy knows the fruit is a real bonus,
因此，最好是充分利用它
so it's best to make the most of it.
伊沙为自己和奥斯卡收集了一堆果子
Isha collects a private stash
for herself and Oscar.
记得吃前要洗洗
Remember to wash your food
before eating it.
然后，就可以嚼成浆了
Once washed,
the fruit is chewed to a pulp
这样所有的养分都能被汲取出来
so all the goodness can be sucked out.
没有牙齿也能照样吃，难怪老爷爷如此喜欢！
You can do it without teeth.
No wonder Grandpa likes them!
这吃相不错
That's a good look.
老爷爷和大家一起其乐融融的场景并不多见
Not a lot of family photos
with Grandpa.
很开胃口
Very appetizing.
果子被吸干后
When the fruit is sucked dry,
浸一下还可以继续
rinse and repeat.
哇 真是不错的好果子！
Wow, that is some good Sacoglottis!
这回小奥斯卡终于不需要妈妈的帮忙了
Finally, this is something Oscar can
eat without his mother's help.
但是没人知道吃了这顿，下顿会在哪里
But it's anyone's guess where
the next meal is coming from.
随着果子渐少
With the fruit running low,
弗雷迪一大家旅游到另一个果园
Freddy's family resorts
to another source of food.
和我们一样，他们也爱吃水果、蔬菜和肉类
Like us, they eat fruits,
vegetables, and meat.
但是他们吃的肉可能会吓你一跳
But their choice in meat is something
that just might surprise you.
猴子
Monkeys.
雄性负责狩猎
The males take up the hunt.
他们分开
They split up.
在林中摆好阵
Fanning out through the forest,
各司其职
they take up their places.
弗雷迪在中间
Freddy is at center stage.
奥斯卡和伊沙在一旁策应
Oscar and Isha watch
from the sidelines.
这些髯猴（产于非洲）成了猎物
These colobus monkeys
are being hunted.
由于体型比黑猩猩灵巧
Smaller and lighter
than the chimpanzees,
他们可以在小树枝间穿梭
they can run on thinner branches,
这使得狩猎更富挑战性
and this makes the hunt
much more challenging.
弗雷迪隐藏起来
Freddy holds back.
没有计划是不行的
This operation requires planning,
而且每个人都要出力
and everyone has a role to play.
他们一个个的悄悄就位
One by one,
they silently take their positions.
猴子们还没注意到他们
The monkeys still haven't seen them.
现在，一个先锋已经上阵
Now, the blockers move up.
他们爬到一个显眼的位置
They're supposed to be seen,
想引起猴子的注意
and take a position in clear view.
另一个先锋
Another blocker.
堵死了另一条出口
Another escape route closed.
弗雷迪渐渐逼近
Freddy climbs carefully.
他必须隐蔽好自己
He must not be seen.
作为一个埋伏者
As ambusher,
弗雷迪在发动进攻前必须悄无声息
Freddy will stay hidden
until he makes the grab.
完美
Perfect.
现在，轮到驱赶者了
Now, for the driver.
他要把猴子赶到伏击者那边
He'll push the monkeys
towards the ambusher.
预备
Ready,
稳住
steady,
进攻！
go!
抓住了一只!
They've got one!
弗雷迪抢了一块最好的肉
Freddy takes the best for himself.
一轮哄抢过后
After the initial scramble,
他们才坐下来慢慢细品
the group settles in for the feast.
对于奥斯卡来说，应该在大人的桌上为自己争个位子
For Oscar, it's time to try to
win a seat at the adult table.
在狩猎中出力的成员先得到肉
Shares get dished out first to those
帮了忙的也能得到奖赏
that helped in the hunt
or as payback for favors.
但是无论如何
But no matter how hard you try,
总有些人觉得自己被蒙骗了
there's always someone
who feels shortchanged.
雌性这时不会大意
The females couldn't care less.
当她们面对想蹭肉的雄猩猩时，
When it comes
to guarding meat from the guys,
姑娘们总能赢
girl power usually wins.
走开, 大块头
Back up, big boy.
饭后来点纤维是最好不过了
It's always good to add
a little fiber to your diet,
所以别忘了旁边的色拉
so don't forget the side salad.
和往常一样，奥斯卡排在最后
As usual, Oscar was last in line,
错失了大餐
so he missed the main course.
他还在吃奶
He'll have to settle
for his mother's milk.
或许他不是大家最喜欢的小孩
He may not be the most popular
little boy with everyone,
但是他总能得到妈妈的关爱
but his mother's love
is something he can count on.
黄昏来临, 美洲豹在地上开始搜寻
With dusk approaching, leopards will
soon prowl the forest floor.
如果伊沙和奥斯卡想睡得安稳，
If Isha and Oscar want to sleep safely,
唯一的办法就是往上爬
the only way is up.
这些小树枝可以织成床垫
Young, flexible branches
can be woven into a platform.
树叶可以拿来垫上
And leaves from the same tree
will do for bedding.
真舒服
Now, that's comfort.
和其他小孩一样，奥斯卡不愿睡觉
Like most kids, Oscar hates bedtime.
最终，伊沙的小淘气捅破了麻布袋
Finally, Isha 's little rascal hits the sack.
即使小孩不吵了
Even if the kids let you sleep,
邻居们还是喋喋不休
there's a good chance
the neighbors will keep you awake.
唉，拜托...
Ah, please...
别开玩笑了行吗？
Are you kidding me?
你知道青蛙也是可以吃的
You know, frogs are edible.
看我的
Here we go.
伊沙和奥斯卡沿着奇路而下
Isha and Oscar go downstairs
the exciting way.
一清早，吃完饭后，
Early morning, just after breakfast,
是相互梳理，培养感情的最佳时刻
is the best time of day to strengthen
friendships with a little grooming.
弗雷迪群里的友谊比以前更加重要了
The bonds between Freddy's team
are more important than ever.
他们远比伤疤的种群小
The group is far smaller
than Scar's rival army
而团队精神是他们保卫坚果园，
and teamwork is their best chance
保障后代生存的关键
of protecting the nut groves
for the next generation.
奥斯卡的未来就在他们手里
Oscar's future is in all their hands.
远在东边，弗雷迪的领地里
Far to the east,
just inside Freddy's territory,
一颗无花果数结满了无花果
a fig tree comes into fruit,
每个人都想要
and is an instant hit with everyone.
无花果是丛林里的救命草
Figs are a lifeline in the forest,
总在没有食物的时候结果
often fruiting when
there is nothing else to eat.
伤疤一伙正在准备突袭
Scar's gang is mounting a raid.
他们吃光了自己家的所有果子
They've wiped out the fruit
in their own territory
饥饿难当，他们越过了边界
and have crossed the border
to satisfy their hunger.
所有的动物都在让路
All other animals scatter.
即使这些无花果也只够他们吃一阵子
Even these figs
won't keep them fed for long.
这只是个权宜之计
This is just a stepping stone.
等时机成熟时
When the moment is right,
他们将要夺过真正的奖励，
they will try to take over the real prize,
坚果园
the nut groves.
伤疤准备在东面发起突袭
Scar's raid on the eastern border
弗雷迪他们毫无察觉
goes unnoticed by Freddy's group.
坚果园里又有一种新的坚果成熟了
A new kind of nut is ripening
in the nut groves.
这些坚果比上次的更硬
These are far tougher
than the last ones.
是时候动用重型装备了
It's time to bring in
the heavy equipment,
强大的工具!
power tools!
锤子的质量直接决定了能否打开坚果
Success with these nuts
is all about the quality of your hammer.
当他们离开捡坚果时，你可以偷偷窃取
You can steal someone else's
while they're off collecting nuts.
弗雷迪就是这方面的专家
And Freddy is an expert at this.
但是对工具别太粗暴
But, man, is he tough on his tools.
这些可是公共财产
These things are
a community resource,
所以能不能别搞破坏？
so can you please
try not to break them?
安全第一!
Safety first!
注意保持手脚和石头的距离
So please keep hands and feet
clear of rocks at all times.
黑猩猩在这里已经砸了4000多年的坚果了
Chimps have gathered here
to crack nuts for over 4, 000 years.
砸坚果已经成了他们的文化遗产之一
Nut-cracking is
part of the group's cultural heritage
一代代薪火相传
and is passed through the generations,
特别是母子相传
especially from mother to child.
对于奥斯卡来说，学习是一个漫长的过程
Learning, for Oscar,
will be a slow process.
拿起一块这样的石头都需要花费他好几年时间
It will be years before he could
even lift a rock like this.
教育他如何在丛林里生存
Day after day,
it takes a committed mom to teach him
是他妈妈的长期义务
how to make a living in the jungle.
伊沙的儿子自力更生还需要好几年
It will be many years
before Isha 's son can fend for himself.
一场风暴让伤疤他们兴奋不已
A gathering storm
excites Scar's forces.
但是对于弗雷迪他们来说，风暴不是什么好事
For Freddy's gang,
the rain is less welcome.
黑猩猩讨厌潮湿
Chimps just hate getting wet.
奥斯卡抱着伊沙取暖
Oscar gets all the warmth
he can from Isha.
伤疤他们一伙
Scar and his gang.
风暴给了他们很好的掩护
The storm is cover for a raid.
这次他们把弗雷迪一伙逼入绝境
This time, they've got them cornered.
伊沙和奥斯卡陷入了危机
Isha and Oscar are in trouble.
伤疤军队势不可挡
Scar's army was overwhelming.
奥斯卡他们零零散散，军心动摇
Oscar's group is in disarray
and badly shaken.
混乱之中，奥斯卡和母亲走散了
In all the chaos,
Oscar lost contact with his mom.
到处不见伊沙的身影
Isha is nowhere to be seen.
伊沙被伤疤他们打伤，不知道逃到了哪里
Isha has been injured and separated
from the group by Scar's gang.
她会努力安全归来
She will struggle to get back safely.
孤独的丛林是如此的凄凉
This is no forest
to be alone in after dark.
伊沙的好几个朋友在走离种群的安全区之后
Several of Isha 's friends
have been lost to leopards,
落入了美洲豹的口中
often when they have strayed
from the safety of the group.
伊沙再也不会回来了
Isha will never return to her family
或者回到奥斯卡身边
or her son.
奥斯卡不知道他的妈妈已经逝去
Oscar doesn't know
about his mother's death
他仍旧到处找妈妈
and he searches for her everywhere.
随着时间流逝，他渐渐感到了孤单
With every hour that slips by,
he becomes more desperate.
奥斯卡处于长身体的时期
Oscar's growing body
needs constant food.
他努力回忆着当初妈妈是怎么谋生的
He tries to remember
what his mom did to make their living.
但是没有她帮忙什么也干不了
But nothing comes easily without her.
日子一天天过去
Hours turn into days.
奥斯卡不能再花太多时间寻找了
Oscar must spend less time searching
他必须花时间想办法谋生
and more time focusing on his survival.
饥饿驱使着奥斯卡来到一个蜜蜂窝前
Hunger drives Oscar to a bees' nest.
蜂蜜是绝佳的食物，但是他以前总是依赖妈妈取蜂蜜
Honey is good food, but he's always
relied on his mom to collect it.
对于小手来说，洞穴太深，而且蜜蜂们很不友善
The honey's too deep for small arms to
reach, and the bees are not happy.
奥斯卡的短板却是弗雷迪的优势
Oscar's loss will be Freddy's gain.
首领拿到了一块最大的蜂蜜
The boss takes the biggest
piece of honeycomb,
人人都有份
but there's enough left
for everyone else,
除了发现它的小奥斯卡
except the little boy who found it.
对于一只年轻饥饿的小黑猩猩来说
The forest seems an
increasingly hostile place
丛林变得越来越充满敌意
for a young, hungry chimpanzee.
这些口齿锋利的蚂蚁军团
The razor-sharp jaws
of these army ants
几分钟之内能剥光一个无花果或是蜥蜴的皮
can strip a frog or a lizard
to the bone in minutes.
把那些能吃掉你的东西当成食物是个好主意吗？
Is it really a good idea to eat
something that can eat you back?
奥斯卡是第一个被咬的
Oscar is the first to get bitten.
没有妈妈，他必须尽快从富有经验的长辈那里学习
Without a mother, he'll need to learn
fast from the older chimps.
总的来说，第一步，
All right, step one,
取手边的树枝做成一个微型钓鱼竿
make a miniature fishing rod
from a nearby branch.
第二步，丢进去等上钩
Step two, cast it in and wait for a bite.
最后, 第三步, 满竿的蚂蚁!
And finally, step three, ants on a stick!
尽情享用吧!
Eat and enjoy!
小伙子，吃得真香啊！
Boy! That is spicy.
真是天才!
It's ingenious!
蚂蚁会咬你的嘴唇,
They will bite your lips,
但你身上其他的地方还是很安全的
but at least the rest of you is safe.
奥斯卡远远躲开
Oscar keeps his distance.
或许吸取经验之后下次会更安全
Maybe it's safer
just to pick up tips for another time.
奥斯卡瘦得很快
Oscar is losing weight quickly,
没有人收留他，
and with no one to groom him,
日子变得越发难熬
it's becoming harder to keep ticks
身上的虫子也越来越多
and other bugs from his skin.
是时候面对现实了
It's time to accept the simple truth.
伊沙不会回来了
Isha isn't coming back.
奥斯卡需要一位新妈妈
Oscar has to find a new mother.
但不幸的是，大部分的雌猩猩都有自己的孩子了
But sadly for him, most of the
females have kids of their own
也帮不上什么忙
and are unable to help.
一次又一次，奥斯卡被拒绝
Again and again, Oscar is rejected.
即使是找个朋友也变得艰难
Even finding a friend seems hard.
形影相吊
It's hopeless.
伤疤他们那天夺走的或许不止一条生命
Scar and his men may have
taken more than one life that day.
敌人又回来了
The enemy has returned.
他们又吃光了家里的果子
They have eaten all the food
in their own territory
现在正准备偷取弗雷迪家的果子，来维持种群的壮大
and are now stealing from Freddy's
land to sustain their number.
对于伤疤来说，群里没有一个好人
For Scar, it's no more Mr. Nice Guy.
他们越来越没耐心了
There is a growing impatience
among Scar's army.
总是想着占领果园
They want to take the nut groves,
不止一个人想造反夺权
and more than one of them
would like to be leader.
奥斯卡使尽了浑身解数
Oscar has tried everything,
但他仍旧单身一人
but he is still alone.
还有最后一只黑猩猩他没接近过
There's only one chimp
he hasn't approached.
弗雷迪
Freddy.
跟着首领，
By following the leader,
奥斯卡至少能找到最好的食物，
Oscar will at least find the best food
明白什么东西能吃
and work out what's safe to eat.
现在，生存才是关键
Right now, survival is all that matters.
弗雷迪不是一个很有耐心的人，
Freddy is not known for his tolerance,
但是奥斯卡也不是存心想找茬
but Oscar isn't a challenger.
这对他们两人都是一段奇妙的经历
This will be
a new experience for them both.
一个温婉的收留是奥斯卡再也期待不过的了
A gentle acceptance is more than
Oscar could have hoped for.
和弗雷迪在一起
Being at Freddy's side
他能学到一些准备食物的经验
should allow him to pick up some
tips on food preparation.
或许大块头的餐桌礼仪
Maybe the big guy's table manners
没有树立最好的榜样
don't set the best example,
但是谁来告诉他呢？
but who's going to tell him off
和他身边的朋友吵一架?
or pick a fight
with the friend sitting next to him?
日子一天天过去
As the days pass, Freddy and Oscar's
弗雷迪和奥斯卡的关系一直没有什么变化
relationship begins to change.
直至一件特殊的事情发生
Until something
extraordinary happens.
弗雷迪允许奥斯卡骑在他的背上
Freddy allows Oscar
to ride on his back
通常只有妈妈才会这样
as usually only a mother would.
这蕴含了一种令人非常难以置信的情感
It's a sign of something truly incredible.
弗雷迪收养了奥斯卡
Freddy will adopt Oscar.
给奥斯卡坚果不会有什么帮助，
Just being led to these nuts
would not help Oscar,
但现在弗雷迪来了，
but now Freddy steps up
他总把自己砸的坚果先分给新朋友奥斯卡
and gives his new friend first pick
of every one he cracks,
就像他曾经的母亲一样
just as his mother once did.
他们的关系越来越好
The bond between them is growing.
这是奥斯卡吃得最香氛的一顿了，自从伊沙消失以来
It's Oscar's best meal
since Isha vanished.
种群正等着首领发话，
The group is waiting for their leader,
但是弗雷迪有他自己的打算
but Freddy has a new project.
奥斯卡成为孤儿后不久，
The learning that stopped short
when Oscar was orphaned
又重拾了昔日的学业
is starting again.
跟着一位聪明熟练的黑猩猩学习
He's with a wise and skilled
chimpanzee who has much to offer.
会议之后继续开讲
Forest school is back in session.
弗雷迪走到哪，奥斯卡跟到哪
Everywhere Freddy goes,
Oscar follows.
弗雷迪做什么，奥斯卡跟着做什么
And everything Freddy does,
Oscar copies.
我们的小家伙快速掌握着丛林法则
Our little boy is
on the fast track to forest knowledge.
有了新朋友之后，弗雷迪的生活更加丰富多彩
Freddy's world may be richer,
thanks to his new friend,
但是担负起了照顾奥斯卡的义务，使得他无暇顾及领土大权
but his commitment to Oscar has left
him no time to patrol his borders.
这一点被某人发现了
The change has been noticed.
伤疤他们现在穿过了边界
Scar and his gang have now
crossed over the ridge.
他们通常不会这么容易就踏进弗雷迪的领土
They would not usually get this deep
into Freddy's land without opposition
他们打算好好把握这个机会
and they intend to take full advantage.
部队在前进之前需要先补给一下
The troops need to refuel
before they push on.
一颗巨大的无花果树遭到掠夺
The grand fig tree is being pillaged.
这是弗雷迪家族赖以生存的食物
This is the food
that Freddy's group were relying on,
但是伤疤可管不了那么多
but Scar has no interest
in the needs of his enemies.
轻而易举的入侵之后，
Encouraged by the lack
of resistance at the border,
掠夺者在弗雷迪的领地更加肆意
the intruders are now
deep inside Freddy's land.
但是队伍里的异议渐起
But there is growing dissent
in the ranks.
这支队伍的作战能力毋庸置疑
The physical power of
this army is beyond question,
但是整个团队也容易打散
but the unity of a team can be fragile.
伤疤需要提防着背后
Scar needs to watch his back.
弗雷迪全身心地投入到奥斯卡身上
Freddy has become
completely devoted to Oscar.
最高级的雄性为最低级的梳理毛发
The highest-ranking male
grooming the lowest.
这真是一个令人吃惊的转变
It's an astonishing turn of events.
数周之前，奥斯卡一无所有
A few weeks ago, Oscar had nothing,
现在吃得好，有人疼
and now he is well fed
and completely adored,
而救他的人却是大家都没想到的
and his savior is the last one
anyone could have expected.
对手吃饱也休息好了
The rivals are fed and rested.
伤疤和他那群暴徒掌控着坚果园
Scar and his mob
are within reach of the nut groves.
全面围攻的时候到了
The time for a full invasion has arrived.
弗雷迪给他的同伴梳理毛发
Freddy grooms his allies.
他知道麻烦正在靠近
He knows there is trouble approaching
这是他第一次紧张了好几周
and for the first time
in weeks, he appears nervous.
友谊需要时间投入，他的注意力开始转移
Friendships need investment,
and his attention has been elsewhere.
奥斯卡注意到了这点
Oscar feels Freddy's focus
drift away from him.
弗雷迪必须让队员明白他还是老大
Freddy must reassure his team
that he is still the boss
他有能力把大家凝聚在一起
and has the strength
to unite them and lead them.
奥斯卡有点不解
Oscar is confused.
他已经失去了一位母亲，似乎又要失去一位父亲
He's lost one parent and
seems to be losing another.
对手正在逼近
The rivals are close.
奥斯卡他们感觉到了不对劲
Oscar and the group
sense that something is wrong.
弗雷迪有所察觉
Something catches Freddy's eye.
伤疤发起了进攻
Scar attacks.
最后一战已经打响
The final push has begun.
弗雷迪他们不能就此逃跑
Freddy's team can't escape.
他们必须迎面而上
They have to fight.
而这时伤疤他们中有人却开始退缩
But some of Scar's mob hold back.
弗雷迪引领进攻
Freddy leads the attack.
两个首领一对一单挑
Freddy and Scar go head-to-head.
胜者只有一个
There can be only one victor.
弗雷迪的鼓声宣告了胜利
Freddy's drum announces victory.
伤疤短期内不会再来了
Scar will not be returning
anytime soon.
团队协作战胜了蛮力攻击
Teamwork has beaten brute force.
几个月之后
队伍正在壮大
The group is now thriving,
他们拥有坚果园的绝对主权
unchallenged in their
ownership of the precious nut groves.
坚果课继续进行，
Cracking school continues,
但是有些学生怎么也学不会
but some students
never seem to catch on.
老爷爷亲眼目睹了伤疤的大败，
Grandpa has lived
to see Scar dealt a blow
或许至此他再也无力东山再起
from which he may never recover.
奥斯卡仍旧麻烦不断
And Oscar is causing
as much trouble as ever,
但是现在他完全融入了大家庭，
but now he's fully
accepted by the group,
成为了每个人的好朋友
and seems to be
everyone's new friend.
或许他们从此过上了恬静的生活
Maybe quiet times are returning at last.
奥斯卡和弗雷迪
Oscar and Freddy
have been transformed
在最后几个月的动乱中都得到了转变
by the turmoil of the last few months.
对于奥斯卡来说，他妈妈的逝去本意味着结束
For Oscar, the loss of his
mother could have meant the end.
但是一个最意外的收养
Instead, it's a new beginning
给了他一个崭新的开始
with the most unlikely foster parent
in the forest.
而弗雷迪呢?
And Freddy?
他发现自己也有温柔的一面
He's discovered a softer side
这一面一定隐藏了很久
that must have been there all along.
有了弗雷迪的保护，
Secure in Freddy's arms,
奥斯卡的未来一片光明
the future finally looks bright for Oscar.
《That Man》 by Caro Emerald
当这个大块头决定收留这个小孤儿，
When this big male decided
to carry this little orphan
照顾他，抚养他时，
and take care of him and give him food,
这逐渐令人叹为观止
it literally took our breath away.
当然，毫无疑问
For sure, there's no doubt
他拯救了一个小生命
he saved the life of the little one.
这一幕真的很感人
And that was really
very touching to see.
当你看到一位妈妈背着她的孩子时，
And when you see a
mother carrying its baby,
真的很温馨.
it's charming.
但是当你看到金刚一样的大块头
But when you see this huge,
King Kong-like figure
背着一个弱小的男孩到处转悠时，
carrying this tiny, little,
male orphan around,
真的很可爱.
it was lovely.
对于他们俩来说
Every single day
was an act of beauty
每一天都是美丽的
between the two of them.
这些让人无法忘怀
And that's something
you can never forget.
有时我会想
Sometimes I imagine
当世界上所有的人
the rest of the world waking up,
都忙着乘公交，乘地铁上班时，
getting on busses,
or they may be getting on subways.
我们的工作就是在丛林中步行一小时，
Our commute to work
is walking for an hour
追寻黑猩猩的足迹
through the jungle
to find chimpanzees.
有些树木令人很难忍受
Some of this stuff is just impenetrable
有些灌木丛很难穿梭过去
and really difficult to move through.
但走在这片丛林里真的很幸福
It really is a joy
to walk through this forest.
你看，并不总是那么容易
You see, it's not always that easy.
我们只有埋头继续前进...
So, we're just walking...
他们在显眼的地方叮你
They bite you
in the most remarkable places.
这群蜂快把我逼疯了
These sweat bees are driving me nuts.
而且，他们不是小蜜蜂
Still, at least they're not honeybees.
啊！啊！啊！
Ahh! Ow! Ow! Ahh!
让人有点受不了了
It's gotten intolerable.
我要走了
I'm leaving.
噢，我的天呐！
Oh, my God. Ed!
如果被咬上一口，你就死定了.
If it bites you, you won't survive.
这可不是在野餐.
It's not a picnic, you know.
很好!
Yes!
肯定还有一条稍简单的路
There must be easier ways
to make a living,
但是也不会好到哪里去
but they're not as much fun.
《Rise》 by Mcclain Sisters
1960年时，有一百万只野生黑猩猩
如今仅剩下1/15
在这里你将知道如何帮忙